<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: international-business | My Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://genejon.es/blog/categories/international-business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://genejon.es/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-10T03:35:26-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://genejon.es/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gene Jones]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Made in the USA: Making Goods at Home]]></title>
    <link href="http://genejon.es/blog/made-in-the-usa-making-goods-at-home/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-24T23:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://genejon.es/blog/made-in-the-usa-making-goods-at-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Why Build Domestic?</h2>

<p>Despite my <a href="http://www.genejon.es/blog/international-business/china-rules-consumer-goods/">previous post</a> it still
makes sense to make consumer goods in the US.</p>

<p>Just to be clear: I am talking real, physical goods here, not software or services.</p>

<h4><strong>Sometimes</strong></h4>

<p>When does it make sense?</p>

<!--more-->


<h5>When it&rsquo;s patriotic</h5>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<h5>When your product needs absolute security.</h5>

<p>National security is a big issue here.
With as much of the US economy being part of the military industrial complex, it can be illegal to source parts from China.</p>

<p>When you can&rsquo;t risk the slightest possible leak, make everyone sign an NDA, threaten to ruin their life if they leak, and then pay well.<br/>
OK, but how many non-military contractor products are truly revolutionary enough to warrant tight security?<br/>
Sure, Apple loves to keep everyone in the dark until the last possible second (as part of their bizare, yet successful marketing strategy).
Who else? No-one? Security is not, outside of national security or unusual circumstances, a major consideration.</p>

<h5>Safety and Quality</h5>

<p>For obvious reasons, foodstuffs are made in the US or Canada. Food spoils, and few want to trust Chinese manufacture with their mouths after various scams.</p>

<p>Highly precise manufacturing also tends to remain in the US or Germany for similiar reasons.</p>

<h5>Small Business</h5>

<p>International Business is hard work. It takes experience, it takes technology, and it takes an open mind. It requires capital, mistakes, and tears.</p>

<p>A small business often can&rsquo;t afford to internationalize. The economies of scale aren&rsquo;t there, inventory headaches can be fatal, and it distracts form their core competencies.</p>

<p>Some startups are designed to scale globally from the ground up. Bully for them, but Mom &amp; Pop stores will continue for a long time.</p>

<p>Take a look at <a href="http://kickstarter.com">Kickstarter</a>; nearly all of those projects, if funded, will be built in someone&rsquo;s garage. The funded individuals will have a hard enough time running a business in their garage, running an international combination of effort will be beyond them.</p>

<h5>Local Goods</h5>

<p>Some goods will never make economic sense to ship across an ocean, regardless of labor costs.</p>

<h5>Customization</h5>

<p>Oh, you wanted 5 of something, rather than 5,000? Yeah, domestic is the way to go.
If you got the design wrong, or they messed it up, it&rsquo;s a ton easier to get changes made.</p>

<p>Customization is hard enough without adding cross-cultural barriers.</p>

<h5>Frequent Iteration</h5>

<p>Similiar to the above, it&rsquo;s impossible to make rapid changes to anything if you have a 20,000 mile supply chain.
Prototypes, rapidly changing fad designs, and 12 hour turnarounds are only possible domestically.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to note that quick changes are an easy place to innovate in hardware, where designs often remain the same for decades.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[China and Patent Law]]></title>
    <link href="http://genejon.es/blog/china-and-patent-law/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-24T23:20:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://genejon.es/blog/china-and-patent-law</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>A Unique Form of Intellectual Property</h2>

<p>China is much maligned on <abbr title="Intellectual Property">IP</abbr> by Western firms.</p>

<h3>Western IP is a Failure</h3>

<p>Arguably, China has a better IP model than do.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The whole idea of Western patent protectionism is generally absurd.
Patents, originally used to protect small inventors from being ripped off by large companies, have been transformed to steal from them.
 Companies like IBM, Microsoft, and Apple have upwards of 30,000 patents apiece, which they use to force cross-licensing agreements with smaller firms.
 Copyright has been distorted into an eternal monopoly, rather than a limited exemption from the public domain.</p>

<p> Patent trolls attack with impunity, waiting until patents nearly expire and then claiming that basic, incredibly obvious ideas like shopping carts are ground-breaking innovations that require millions in payments. The USPTO is so bad at granting stupidly obvious applications that they are <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-19672986">now asking for crowdsourcing</a> of patent invalidation.</p>

<p> Is it any wonder patent law is one of the best paying fields in America?</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I&rsquo;m willing to go thermonuclear war on this</p><footer><strong>Steve Jobs</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Steve Jobs wasn&rsquo;t talking about nukes. He was talking about patents.</p>

<h3>A More Excellent Way</h3>

<p>In China, they follow the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beerware">beerware</a> model. It relies upon a shared community ethos rather than a strict legal system. Will this system last?</p>

<p>Nobody knows. But it&rsquo;s better than <a href="http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2013/04/meet-the-nice-guy-lawyers-who-want-1000-per-worker-for-using-scanners/">getting sued for using a scanner</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[China Rules Consumer Goods]]></title>
    <link href="http://genejon.es/blog/china-rules-consumer-goods/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-24T23:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://genejon.es/blog/china-rules-consumer-goods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>How China Rules Consumer Goods</h2>

<p>Made in the USA.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a funny statement, mostly because of how few consumer goods are <em>made in the USA</em>.</p>

<p>As a child born in the 90&rsquo;s, I can only remember a few products with that origin label. My toys started out as &lsquo;Made in Mexico&rsquo;, some of my electronics said &lsquo;Made in Japan&rsquo;; pretty much everything else had the ubiquitous &lsquo;Made in China&rsquo;.</p>

<p>How did nearly all consumer oriented manufacture shift from the US?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Cheap Labor</h3>

<p>Labor was comparatively expensive here in the US of A. Very, very comparatively expensive.</p>

<p>Without even getting into unions, minimum hourly wage alone makes labor sourcing non-competitive.</p>

<p>Consumer goods are labor intensive. We forget that, we think that robots can do everything, and do it for cheaper than humans.</p>

<p>Now of course, it&rsquo;s impossible to come back.</p>

<h3>Locus of Innovation</h3>

<p>It used to be you made your goods in China because it was cheaper to build them there.</p>

<p>Now, you build in China because it logistically doesn&rsquo;t make any sense to build elsewhere. All parts can be sourced within 30 miles of each other; only exiting that 30 mile block on a shipping container bound for the Western coastline. This tight of an integration is difficult in the US and elsewhere; we simply don&rsquo;t have that central manufacturing zone.</p>

<p>Beyond this, Shenzen has critical mass, a teeming marketplace of innovation. As an electronics hobbyist, 60% of the datasheets I come across have Mandarin on them. The chemical processes, the warehouses, the materials, the practical know-how &mdash; and more &mdash; is there.</p>

<p>We don&rsquo;t know all the tricks anymore. China out innovates us when it comes to making cheap goods. They make a <a href="http://blog.makezine.com/2013/04/22/the-12-cellphone/">$12 cellphone</a> without subsidy or expected carrier return. Sure, the industrial design isn&rsquo;t the best, but that will come with maturity.</p>

<h3>Regulatory Barriers</h3>

<p>If you want to build your next electronic wizmo in the US, go right ahead! Nobody will stop you.</p>

<p>You will, however need to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Build a factory (which complies to OSHA &amp; EPA standards)</li>
<li>Source <strong>all</strong> your parts from the US, or risk weeks of delays</li>
<li>Find people willing to work at your factory

<ul>
<li>who are skilled at manufacture</li>
<li>who want $20/hour</li>
<li>who aren&rsquo;t going to unionize</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Deal with lawsuits of all kinds, warranted and unwarranted</li>
</ul>


<p>Not all of the above are bad things. I certainly want to make more than $20 an hour (and in fact, I do), and I like knowing my office lacks amenities like asbestos. But they sure make it hard to compete with China on consumer goods outside of niche areas.</p>

<p>There are many risks to outsourcing, but never forget that it&rsquo;s very risky to do business in the US too. It&rsquo;s a familiar risk, a risk we are acclimated to, and thus a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Risk_compensation">risk we should be all the more fearful of</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
