<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: code | My Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://genejon.es/blog/categories/code/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://genejon.es/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-10T02:59:48-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://genejon.es/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gene Jones]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Sane Blog: Switching from Wordpress to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://genejon.es/blog/2013/04/12/a-sane-blog-switching-from-wordpress-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-12T23:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://genejon.es/blog/2013/04/12/a-sane-blog-switching-from-wordpress-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In what (<em>hopefully</em>) is my final blog website change before I sit down and actually type some blog posts, I&rsquo;ve migrated over to Octopress.</p>

<h2>Why Did You Move Sites <strong>Again</strong></h2>

<p>I used to host this site with Wordpress, powered by the good folk over at <a href="https://www.nearlyfreespeech.net/">NearlyFreespeech</a> (who offer fantastically cheap rates).
But while Wordpress had a great community, constant bug fixes, and millions of tutorials, there was always something that felt wrong.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Wordpress always struck me a little odd.</p>

<ul>
<li>Wordpress can be slow</li>
<li>It was expensive to host, due to</li>
<li>a database requirement</li>
<li>Wordpress is a complicated beast, and writing even a basic theme is the task of many a tutorial.</li>
<li>Wordpress can have tons of security vulnerabilities.</li>
</ul>


<p>Worst of all, <em>Wordpress is written in <strong>PHP</strong></em>, the <em><a href="http://me.veekun.com/blog/2012/04/09/php-a-fractal-of-bad-design/">devil&rsquo;s programming language</a></em>.</p>

<p>I once wrote a site in PHP. Once.
<blockquote><p>How can you even be a PHP programmer without a sense of humor? You write PHP. That&rsquo;s hilarious.</p><footer><strong>@codinghorror <a href="https://twitter.com/codinghorror/status/224269282396225536">https://twitter.com/codinghorror/status/224269282396225536</a></strong></footer></blockquote>
How could I ever make changes to a PHP powered site, and keep myself sane?</p>

<p>I looked around for alternatives for quite some time, and it seemed my search was in vain.</p>

<p>I have a&hellip;<em>unique</em> list of requirements for a blog framework:</p>

<ul>
<li>I need the ability to self host. It can be on someone else&rsquo;s server, but I need the HTML to be on my hard drive, scattered on random flash drives. I don&rsquo;t want a host to go under and lose all my work. I even run my <a href="yourls.org">own link shortner, YOURLS</a>, for fear of VC money running out at all the main link shortening firms. A Tumblr was out of the question. I eventually conceded that <a href="http://genejones.quora.com">Quora</a> makes for a decent micro-blogging platform, but I still needed a full-sized blog.</li>
<li>Custom domains are a must. The domain hack of GeneJon.es (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.es">thanks Spain!</a>) is too good to pass up. A ton of hosted sites only allow for .net, .com, and other boring TLDs, so they were a no-go.</li>
<li>I like Open source, and might want to tweak a few things under the hood later.</li>
</ul>


<p>Eventually I found a few flat-file blog frameworks, but they lacked something I desperately needed: good looking themes.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been cursed by having a graphic designer for a mother.
In my primitive youth, I once considered Adobe Indesign <em>a fun computer game</em>.
I know some of typography, even if by accident of my birth. I can see good design, and I appreciate it.
I loathed the crappy 2004 era themes that the flat-file frameworks offered me.
I harshly judged sites with similiar appeareance.
I love substance in a blog, yes, but I stay for style of all kinds: style in the theme, style in the writing, style of personality.<br/>
But while I can <em>see</em> good design, I am not very good at <em>making</em> good design.</p>

<p>CSS isn&rsquo;t my strong suite.
After spending hours upon hours trying to learn it&rsquo;s intricacies only to end up with horrible, miserable looking webpages, I conceded defeat.
Moreover, the idea of taking an existing theme, and smushing another framework into it, was abhorent to me (and time consuming).</p>

<h4>Finding Octopress</h4>

<p>Eventually I heard of something called Jeykll. It seemed like a cool idea, but it also seemed like a ton of work.</p>

<p>After attending a few Javascript meetups, I decided to embark on the creation of a staticly hosted Single Page Application.
It would be the Apex of Ajax. I even kinda-sorta <a href="https://github.com/genejones/north-american-hipster">got it to work</a> before I tired of feeding the Javascript, and returned to the safety of Python.
A Django blog seemed like such overkill as to be laughable, and the formatting would have sucked.
My ego is not sufficient to suffer with a terrible blog site backend just because I wrote it.</p>

<p>I resigned myself to Wordpress.
It wouldn&rsquo;t be so bad, look at all those features!
But I still lingered for more.</p>

<p>As I kept seeing more and more sites hosted on github, it was obvious there was some kind of framework behind this upswell.
And then, low and behold: &ldquo;Powered by <a href="octopress.org">Octopress</a>&rdquo;. It was perfect.</p>

<p>Octopress has a nice theme out of the box, much like Wordpress does.
And the <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/wiki/3rd-Party-Octopress-Themes">Third Party themes</a> are even better, and more are being created constantly as new folks join on the Octopress bandwagon.</p>

<p>I found the <a href="https://github.com/sevenadrian/foxslide">FoxSlide theme</a> and here we are.</p>

<p>All this text without even mentioning all the technical benefits. When it comes to a personal blog, <a href="http://highscalability.com/blog/2011/8/22/strategy-run-a-scalable-available-and-cheap-static-site-on-s.html"><strong>Go Static or Go Home</strong></a> (really).</p>

<ul>
<li>CDN, caching, etc. make static sites <em>blazing fast</em></li>
<li>Revision Control? Heck yes!</li>
<li>Simple text files. Beautiful, editable text files.</li>
</ul>


<p>I learned how to do a Ruby install on Windows for you, Octopress.
I&rsquo;m never going to give you up now.<br/>
And if that&rsquo;s not an example of the sunk cost fallacy, I don&rsquo;t know what is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
